{
  "reference_number": "1127",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "Planting of non-harvested forests to offset agriculture emissions e.g.in East Cape where the soils are eroded via storms"
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "With a planned approach, business will respond more quickly. For example, if we make a hard line ban on the sale of all petrol or\n\ndiesel fueled vehicles by, say 2035, then importers will know they have to ramp up the sources of battery powered vehicles to sell in\nthe NZ market. They will have 17 years to prepare for 100% BEV sales."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "All elements of the business sector, the transport sector, energy generators and suppliers, technology innovation and development."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Business and technology innovation development are essential elements when developing plans. They are essential if we want to\n\nget buy in and make critical technology direction decisions. For example, choosing hydrogen as the \"fuel of the future\" to power a fuel\ncell to generate electricity that charges a battery to power an electric motor for propulsion, would be a dumb move, when considering\n\nthe current hydrocarbon source and costs to produce the gas, plus the CO2 emissions as part of the production process. However, if\nan inexpensive, mobile, fast, and safe form of electrolysis process can be developed and scaled, where the source is water and the\nemissions are H2O, then that route may present itself as a feasible alternative fuel to the plug in BEV."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "In may respects, NZ needs to follow China's playbook, particularly in respect to a form of central planning. It will mean we can have a\n\ncoordinated plan that covers all sectors of the economy, to meet a well defined goal."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "That will be a necessary function if we are to understand the inputs and outputs of each sector of the economy, and can model and\ntweak the plan to balance any \"pain points\" fairly."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Every BEV imported into NZ will be fueled from indigenous sources over its lifetime. In contrast, every petrol or diesel vehicle,\nincluding hybrids, will require NZ to continue to import oil to fuel that vehicle over its lifetime. The sooner we get the planned targets\nin place, the better off we will be. Investment and business decisions are generally multi-year choices, and the government has\n\nresponsibility to provide clear directions across all sectors of the economy. Aggressive targets will need some hard selling, but we can\nfollow other markets where these signals have already been made. For example, bans on sale of petrol or diesel vehicles after 2040\n\nin the UK and sooner in other countries, getting the power grid to 100% renewables as in Iceland. Incentives and disincentives to\npush change will be needed. For example, a surcharge on the sticker price of petrol and diesel fueled vehicles, including hybrids, with\nthe proceeds to be used to fund charging infrastructure. NZTA to collect the odometer readings at registration time to enable the\n\ncalculation of a usage charge to eventually replace fuel taxes. Registration fees to be minimal for BEVs for the first 5 years, while\nincreasing on a scale for petrol and diesel vehicles."
    }
  ]
}
